<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>Caselaw Research</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/Viewer.swf?slide={position}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>Case Reporters, Digests  &amp; Their Alternatives</title>
		<content>Case Reporters, Digests 
&amp; Their Alternatives Chapter 9 </content>
		<related-content>&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Research Process</title>
		<content>Research Process Analyze your facts(Things, Relief, causes of Action and defenses, People, Places) Secondary Sources Common Law or Statutory Law? Common LawRead cases referenced in Secondary SourcesUse Digests to find cases StatutoryUse Annotated CodeUpdate code with pocket part and Legislative Service Shepardize or Keycite casesRead cases Shepardize code  sectionRead cases cited in code section         </content>
		<related-content>Today we will be discussing case law, also known as common law.  Case law is a type of primary law that is derived from judicial decisions as opposed to statutes or constitutions.  In the research process, case law generally follows researching with secondary sources.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Hierarchy of Legal Authority</title>
		<content>Hierarchy of Legal Authority   Cases – must be consulted in interpreting Constitution, statutes, and agency rules and regulations </content>
		<related-content>Before we begin our coverage of case law, let’s review some of the concepts we discussed earlier in Sources of Legal Authority.  As you know, constitutions, statutes, rules and regulations are all examples of primary law.  These laws tend to be broad in scope and often need additional explanation to really be effective.  This is where case law comes in.  Case law interprets (and often clarifies) the laws of constitutions, statutes and rules and regulations. &lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Hierarchy of Legal Authority</title>
		<content>Hierarchy of Legal Authority   Parallel Systems   </content>
		<related-content>Case law is found at both the state and federal level.  As you can see the state and federal court systems share similarities in their organizational structure.  As a general rule, the Supreme Court will be the highest court, followed by the Court of Appeals (the intermediary court) and the Trial Courts (the lowest level of court).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, not all state courts use the same terms to refer to their courts and not all state courts have an intermediate level of review.  For example the  highest court in New York  is the Court of Appeals, while the New York Supreme Court is actually the trial court.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The distinction between court levels in the hierarchy of legal authority becomes especially important when using case law because it is necessary to understand the level of authority of each case you plan on presenting to the court.  As a general rule, lower courts must always follow the case law issued by the courts above them.  However, higher courts may choose to follow or not follow the case law issued by courts beneath them.  We will discuss this concept  further as we continue in this lesson.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>What is a Case?</title>
		<content>What is a Case?   </content>
		<related-content>So, what is a case?  A case is the published opinion of a court regarding a legal dispute.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Most cases start in the trial court and may end up later being appealed to a higher court –either an appellate court or a supreme court.  The published opinions of these appellate or supreme courts make up most of the cases that you will find in your research.  These cases are published in books called case reporters or reporters, which are also available electronically through Westlaw and Lexis.  Let’s look at how a case appears in a reporter.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Anatomy of a Case</title>
		<content>Anatomy of a Case  Parallel Citation Parties Docket Number Court Decision Date Synopsis         </content>
		<related-content>Here we are looking at the case of Day v. Beau Townsend Ford, which has been published in the North Eastern Reporter.  We will use the Day case to explore the main components of a legal opinion.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;First, let’s look at the parallel citation.  A parallel citation is an additional reference to a case that has been reported in more than one reporter.  For example, Day v. Beau Townsend Ford, has been cited in 2 reporters –the North Eastern Reporter 2nd series and the Ohio Appellate Reporter 3rd series.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Next we can see the names of the parties involved in the case –Day (the appellants) and Beau Townsend Ford (the appellee).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is followed by the docket number.  A docket is a formal record in which a judge or court clerk briefly notes all the proceedings and filings in a court case.   The docket number is the number assigned by the court clerk to the case and it is one of the first numbers assigned to case that has not yet been published.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Next is the name of the court that rendered the decision, in this case the Ohio Court of Appeals, and the date of decision.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is followed immediately by the synopsis of the case.  The synopsis is a one paragraph overview of the facts and outcome of the case.  It is written by the publisher’s staff not the court rendering the decision.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>   Headnotes Lawyers Judge MajorityOpinion  [2] Reference to Headnote 2 Judgment  Star Pagination         </content>
		<related-content>Further down we can see the headnotes listed out.  A headnote is  the summary of the case that appears before the printed judicial opinion in a law report. Headnotes are comprised of topics and keynumbers.  Each headnote is numbered and addresses a specific point of law in the case, including the relevant facts regarding that point of law.   As you read through the text of the case, where the topics covered by the headnotes appear you will see a headnote reference. The headnote reference is represented by a bracketed number that corresponds to the headnote it represents.  In this case the bracketed number 2 on page 771 is meant to tell the reader that  this section of the text encompasses the point of law referenced in headnote 2.  Note: Headnotes are written by the  publisher’s staff not the court rendering the decision.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;After the heanotes, the names of attorneys who represented each party and the name of the judge writing the opinion appears.  The opinion follows directly after the judge’s name.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An opinion is a court’s written statement explaining its decision in a given case.  If an opinion is agreed upon by  more than half of the judges hearing the case it is called a majority opinion.  If an opinion does not have enough judges’ votes to constitute a majority, but receives more votes than any other opinion, it is called a plurality opinion.  In the Day case 2 of the 3 judges agreed with the opinion issued so it would be called a majority opinion.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As you are looking at the components of a case you should note that only the opinion of the court constitutes legal authority.  All of the remaining items are editorial enhancements.  These editorial enhancements are very useful for locating cases, but they are not part of the court’s opinion.  You should never rely on any part of a case other than the text of the opinion itself.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As you are reading through case law you may also see references to star pagination.  Star pagination is a system in reprinted editions of court reports to show where the pages of the text of the official edition begin and end.  In print the star pagination symbol is represented by an upside down T.  Star pagination is also used online with Westlaw and Lexis , where it is denoted by the star symbol.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The court’s judgment, is generally the last piece of  the opinion, where the court states its decision as to the legal outcome of the case.  In the Day case, the court concluded that the trial court was correct and affirmed its decision.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>   Dissent  </content>
		<related-content>Any dissenting or concurring opinions will appear immediately after the court’s holding.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A dissenting opinion is an opinion by one or more judges who disagree with the decision reached by the majority.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A concurring opinion is an opinion by one or more judges who agree with the decision reached by the majority, but who may have different grounds for explaining  why the decision reached is correct.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Dissenting and concurring opinions may have valuable legal arguments contained within them, however they are not binding.  Concurring and dissenting opinions only have the effect of a persuasive source of law.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Stare Decisis &amp; Precedent</title>
		<content>Stare Decisis &amp; Precedent    </content>
		<related-content>Now that we are familiar with the anatomy of a case, let’s look at some of the other factors that may affect your decision to cite to specific case law.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;First, let’s look at the doctrine of precedent and stare decisis.  Stare decisis is latin for “to stand by things decided.” It is the doctrine of precedent which requires a court to follow earlier judicial decisions when the same question arises again in litigation. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Following precedent ensures that cases with similar facts are treated consistently.  Conforming the way similar cases are handled by the court also allows for predictability and stability in the law.   &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, there are situations where a court will not follow precedent.  In those cases the court may choose to distinguish an earlier case by finding factual differences between it and the pending case; then the court may apply a different rule to the case before it.  A court may also modify common law by revising the rule in a new case or the court may even overrule precedent in response to a significant need for change.  Note: The legislature may also enact a statute modifying common law.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When you are considering presenting a case before a court you should consider whether the case you are citing reflects law that has already been followed by the court.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Mandatory v. Persuasive</title>
		<content>Mandatory v. Persuasive Primary Mandatory Primary Persuasive Court of AppealsTrial Court Supreme CourtCourt of Appeals   </content>
		<related-content>Another point to consider when choosing to cite a case, should be whether the court you are citing the case to&lt;i&gt; needs &lt;/i&gt;to follow the case.  Whether a court needs to follow the case you are citing will depend on the weight of authority given to the case.  To do this you will need to establish if the case you are working with is mandatory authority or persuasive authority.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Case law is by nature a primary source, but determining whether a case is Primary &lt;br&gt;Mandatory Authority or Primary Persuasive Authority will depend on your Jurisdiction&lt;br&gt;and the Level of Court you are citing the case to.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A primary mandatory  authority is law that a particular court must follow.  This means that a court is bound by decisions of higher courts and by its own decisions.  However, it is not bound by decisions by other courts at the same level or by lower courts.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A primary persuasive authority is law that a court may choose to follow, but does not have to follow.  For example, a court may choose to follow the ruling of a lower court or of a court at the same level.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A case can even be both primary mandatory and primary persuasive authority depending on how it is used, for example:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When a case from an appellate court is cited to a trial court, the appellate court case is PRIMARY MANDATORY authority.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When the same case from that appellate court is cited to the Supreme court, the appellate court case is PRIMARY PERSUASIVE authority.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You should always look for cases that are primary mandatory authority that support your position to cite  because unless the court can distinguish the case or chooses to overrule it, the court will be forced to follow the law as reported in those cases.  You would only want to cite to primary persuasive law if there were not primary mandatory authority available for your legal issue.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Note: Secondary Sources are always persuasive authority&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Courts Where Appeals Are Normally Filed</title>
		<content>Courts Where Appeals Are Normally Filed Cases Appealed FromU.S. Supreme CourtU.S. Court of AppealsState Supreme CourtState Court of AppealsU.S. Court of AppealsXU.S. District CourtsIf issued by a 3-judge panel OR when the U.S., its agent or employee is a party, and an act of Congress is held unconstitutional on its face (not as applied)XState Supreme CourtsIf a federal question is involvedXState Courts of AppealIf a federal question is involved, and the State Supreme Court has denied relief OR declined to hear the caseXState Trial CourtsIf there’s no court of appeal OR it is a special case (appeal of a death penalty case)X </content>
		<related-content>Another way to thinks of it is to see where your case would be appealed if it were to go on in litigation.  The decisions of any court that is high enough to hear an appeal of your case would be considered mandatory authority to the lower court that you are citing to.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Reported v. Unreported</title>
		<content>Reported v. Unreported       </content>
		<related-content>Another consideration in choosing case law is the status of the case –is it reported or unreported.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reported cases are opinions that are published in print official reporters. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In Ohio the official reporters  where reported cases can be found are :&lt;br&gt;Ohio State Reports –All Ohio Supreme Court cases &lt;br&gt;Ohio Appellate Reports –Selected Appellate cases&lt;br&gt;Ohio Miscellaneous Reports –Selected Trial Court cases (common pleas, municipal, etc.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Decisions not designated for publication by the court are called unpublished, or non-&lt;br&gt;precedentail opinions.  In the past, the only way to obtain copies of unpublished decisions&lt;br&gt;were from the parties to the case or from the clerk’s office at the courthouse.  This is still true&lt;br&gt;for some unpublished decisions, especially those issued by state courts.  However, many&lt;br&gt;unpublished decisions are available through Westlaw and Lexis and other online sources.  As&lt;br&gt;a general rule, unreported cases are not treated as binding cases on the courts.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, you should note that in Ohio there is some disagreement as to whether unpublished &lt;br&gt;opinions may be cited as precedent.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Before May 1, 2002: &lt;/b&gt;Published opinions were considered controlling authority in the&lt;br&gt;district in which they were decided and could be cited as persuasive authority to&lt;br&gt;other districts.  Unpublished opinions were controlling only as to the parties and&lt;br&gt;could only be cited in limited circumstances such as (1) as authority between parties&lt;br&gt;(2) in the district it was rendered, as persuasive only (3) by an appellate court of&lt;br&gt;another district to certify a question to the Ohio Supreme Court.  Rationale for the &lt;br&gt;old rule: impossible to print all appellate decisions and computerized legal research &lt;br&gt;not widely accessible.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;After May 1,&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt; 2002:&lt;/b&gt; Court of Appeals opinions issued after May 1, 2002 may be cited&lt;br&gt;as legal authority and &lt;i&gt;weighted as deemed appropriate &lt;/i&gt;by the courts. Rationale for&lt;br&gt;new rule: many appellate judges gave equal weight to published and unpublished&lt;br&gt;opinions  anyway and technology now permits appellate opinions to be easily&lt;br&gt;accessed electronically.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Finding Case Law</title>
		<content>Finding Case Law PrintWestlawLexis </content>
		<related-content>Now that we know what we’re looking for in a case, let’s talk about how to actually do the research.  We’ll begin with a little background on how cases are found in print and then we will move on to finding cases using Westlaw and Lexis.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Reporters</title>
		<content>Reporters   </content>
		<related-content>As I mentioned earlier, cases are published in books called reporters.  The cases are  published in the reporters in chronological order.  Many reporters are limited to cases from specific jurisdictions or court level.  For example, federal reporters contain opinions from federal courts and state reporters contain opinions from state courts.  In addition, reporters may also be divided into different series based on the time period they cover.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There are 2 types of reporters: official and unofficial.  A reporter published by the government is called an official reporter.  A reporter published by a commercial publisher like Westlaw or Lexis is called an unofficial reporter.  If is possible for a case to appear in both types of reporter, however the text of the case should be exactly the same in both the official and unofficial reporter.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Here is an example of state cases that are published in West’s Regional Reporters.&lt;br&gt;Ohio cases are found in the North Eastern Reporter.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The North Eastern Reporter is the unofficial reporter for Ohio. In Ohio, the official reporters are :&lt;br&gt;Ohio State Reports –All Ohio Supreme Court cases &lt;br&gt;Ohio Appellate Reports –Selected Appellate cases&lt;br&gt;Ohio Miscellaneous Reports –Selected Trial Court cases (common pleas, municipal, etc.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>Digests</title>
		<content>Digests   </content>
		<related-content>Since case reporters are published in chronological order and are not organized by subject, trying to research cases in chronological order would be very difficult.  For example, you are trying to locate case law on a slip and fall case.  Your client was shopping at Krogers, slipped on a grape in the produce aisle and as a result needs to have surgery on her ankle.  You can probably think of several terms that would help you in your research like personal injury, negligence, hazardous condition and so on but which dates will these cases appear in the reporter?  Are negligence cases only published in the month of December? Are personal injury cases only published in February on a leap year?  No!  What about skimming through the reporters to find cases?  Case reporters are too big to even think about reading though from cover to cover to find case law.  It would be a very long and frustrating experience.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So how can you find cases related to your topic?  You will want to use a digest.  Digests organize the cases found in case reporters into subjects.  Digests are finding tools that allow you to use your search terms like personal injury and negligence to find appropriate cases in the reporter.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Ohio Digest &amp; Reporter</title>
		<content>Ohio Digest &amp; Reporter  West’s Ohio Digest North Eastern Reporter   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;br&gt;In Ohio, West's Ohio Digest provides a subject index to cases. It contains brief summaries of both State and Federal Ohio cases. The summaries are grouped into topics- for example Appeal and Error, Corporations, Taxation, etc. Each topic has an outline, and each subtopic in the outline is assigned a "key number" (for example, Corporations k46 - Acting in False or Assumed Name). When you find a good key number, you find summaries of cases on the point of law in question.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As we saw earlier, Ohio cases are represented in the North Eastern Reporter.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you were going to look for Ohio case law using the print resources you would start by looking up your terms in the  Ohio digest and locating appropriate case law.  Then you would take your list of cases and look them up in the North Eastern Reporter, where you could read the text of the case in its entirety. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title>West Key Numbers</title>
		<content>West Key Numbers Topics are subdivided into smaller categoriesEach subdivision is assigned a Key NumberCase summaries in West Digests 	appear under relevant Key Number  </content>
		<related-content>One of the strongest features of  West  publications is the Key Number System.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The Key Number System is like a really big outline of legal topics.  It works by: First, it breaks down the American system of law into over 400 Major Topics.  Each of those topics is divided, in greater and greater detail, into individual units that represent a specific legal concept -- like steps in an outline. Each of the lines has a unique number that allows you to find it on the outline. This number is called a Key Number. The whole outline, along with the case headnotes classified to it, is called the Key Number System.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title>Using Digests in Print</title>
		<content>Using Digests in Print Chapter 9CALI “How to Find Case Law Using the Digests”To Access CALI lessons:Go to www.cali.org/registerCreate a username and password using the authorization code CINCINstu42 </content>
		<related-content>There are many steps for researching case law using case reporters and digests in print.  In this lecture we will concentrate on how to find case law solely by using electronic resources.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For additional information about finding case law using print resources please refer to Chapter 9 of your textbook and the CALI lesson “How to Find Case Law Using the Digests.”&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="20" xmlns="">
		<title>Researching Cases Electronically</title>
		<content>Researching Cases Electronically Main Methods of Case Law Research: Find by Citation, Party Name or Docket NumberTerms &amp; Connectors or Natural Language SearchSearch Key Numbers (Westlaw) or Headnotes (Lexis) Cited in Secondary SourcesCited in Annotated CodesUsing Citators </content>
		<related-content>West's digest  system is also available online through Westlaw and Lexis has a similar feature called Lexis headnotes, which is available online through Lexis.  We will look at some of the key differences in how case law is found using both Westlaw and Lexis using find by citation, terms &amp;amp; connectors, natural language, key numbers and headnotes.  Locating case law in secondary sources was previously covered in your lesson on secondary sources and you will learn how to locate case law using annotated code and citators in your lessons on statutes and citators.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000020.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="21" xmlns="">
		<title>Finding a Case by Citation</title>
		<content>Finding a Case by Citation 717  N.E.2d  769 Volume Number Reporter Page Number    </content>
		<related-content>Retrieving  a case by legal citation is the easiest and fastest way to get the information that you want, namely the specific case the citation refers to.  In order to find a case by citation you need to have three basic components: (1) the volume number of the reporter that case was found in (2) the abbreviated name of the reporter and (3) the page number the case was found on in the reporter.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000021.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="22" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>     Volume Reporter Page   </content>
		<related-content>Let’s use our earlier example, Day v. Beau Townsend Ford.  The legal citation for Day v. Beau Townsend Ford, is 717 N.E.2d 769.  This citation is showing that the case was found on page  769 of volume 717 of the North Eastern Reporter 2nd series.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000022.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="23" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Let’s use our citation information to search for Day v. Beau Townsend Ford on Westlaw.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To find a case by citation, you should select the Find &amp;amp; Print link at the top of the Westlaw screen.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;On the left hand side of the page, enter your citation in the find this document by citation box, then select go.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Note: If you did not have a case citation you could also search by party name.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000023.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="24" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Notice the link to the West Reporter Image.  Opening this link will allow you to see the case exactly as it appeared in print.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000024.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="25" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>As you can see, it looks identical to the print version of the case.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000025.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="26" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>If we go back to the original screen and scroll down, notice the star pagination.  Star pagination refers back to the original reporter pages.  Since the Day case has been published in both the North Eastern Reporter and the Ohio Appellate Reports, Westlaw represents the page numbering from those sources with one star for pages from the Ohio Appellate Reports and two stars for pages from the North Eastern Reporter.  Here we can see the name of the attorney for the appellants, John Limoli, appeared on page 265 of the Ohio Appellate Reporter and page 770 of the North Eastern Reporter.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000026.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="27" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>You can also find a case by citation, party name or docket number using the Get a Document tab on Lexis.  Here we will enter our citation for the Day case and select get.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000027.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="28" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Lexis also uses star pagination.  Looking at the citations at the top of the case, you can easily see that Lexis is designating pages from the Ohio Appellate Reporter with one star, pages from the North Easter Reporter with two stars and pages from Lexis’ own citation for the case with three stars.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000028.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="29" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Note: You can also click on the more like this headnote link or the headnote topic all link to get additional cases on this topic.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000029.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="30" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Here we can see the layout of the rest of the case on Lexis.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000030.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="31" xmlns="">
		<title>Search Techniques</title>
		<content>Search Techniques Terms &amp; Connectors Natural Language Example: bankrupt! w/25 discharg!AND (student or college or educationw/5 loan)Use when searching for:Comprehensive information about an issue or topic, or a person or companyEvery word or its alternative that appears in each documentSpecific relationships between your search wordsDocument section-specific searches Example: Can a student loan bedischarged in bankruptcy?Use when searching for:Researching conceptual issues rather than highly specific topicsResearching complex issues when you don't know what words to useObtaining help in writing a search description, including automatic phrase identification and access to an online thesaurusSupplementing a Terms and Connectors search to ensure thorough results </content>
		<related-content>While retrieving a case by citation is easy, most of the time when you are researching you will not have a specific citation at hand.  You will begin your research with only a limited fact pattern and a legal question you need to answer.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Terms &amp;amp; Connectors or Natural Language searches allow you to formulate searches specific to the legal question you are trying to answer and allow you to select which type of database (case law, secondary sources, state, federal ,etc.) you would like to search in.&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;Terms and connectors (or Boolean) searching is a way to construct queries using true-false connectors. Boolean searching is a very powerful search technique and has become the conventional method for most computerized searching.   You may already be familiar with some common connectors such as AND, OR, and the Wildcard (*).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Natural language searches let you enter a search in plain English, without having to use any special terms or connectors. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This slide illustrates when it is best to use terms &amp;amp; connectors versus natural language searching.   You will learn more about terms and connectors and natural language searching in another lesson, but we will cover some basic examples here.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000031.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="32" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>To use natural language or terms &amp;amp; connectors to search for state case law in Westlaw, select the Directory link at the top of the screen.  The select U.S. State Materials.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000032.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="33" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Since we will continue our search with the Day case, we will select Ohio.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000033.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="34" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Then Cases.  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000034.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="35" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Since we know this is an Ohio Court of Appeals case we will select the Ohio State Courts database (OH-CS).  &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000035.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="36" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>We now have the option to search by using either terms &amp;amp; connectors or natural language.  For the purposes of this example, we will run a terms and connectors search to find any cases where the word lemon appears within 2 words of law and those words appear within 25 words of trust.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000036.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="37" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>And  we can see our search was successful since the Day case appears in our results list.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000037.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="38" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>To use natural language or terms &amp;amp; connectors to search for state case law in Lexis, select the Legal tab.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000038.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="39" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Scroll down and select Ohio.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000039.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="40" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Select Ohio state cases combined&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000040.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="41" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>This time we will run a natural language search for all Ohio state cases that deal with the question “Are leased vehicles covered under Ohio’s lemon law?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000041.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="42" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>And again the Day case appears in our results list.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000042.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="43" xmlns="">
		<title>Using Headnotes</title>
		<content>Using Headnotes Case LawSecondary SourcesAnnotated CodesKey Numbers </content>
		<related-content>Headnotes in cases are an easy access point for getting into the online digest.  This is helpful because it can help you quickly find a large amount of case law  covering your specific legal topic.  You can locate headnotes by using a known case, secondary source or annotated code.  You can also locate headnotes by searching using the Key Number link at the top of the screen.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000043.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="44" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>In the Day Case, we can see headnote one contains a specific topic and key number for lemon laws.  By clicking on the keynumber for lemon laws we can search for other cases on the same topic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Note: Lemon Laws were formerly under Consumer Protection&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000044.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="45" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>We will choose Kentucky as our jurisdiction.  Note: We could also add specific search terms to the search box if we wanted to further narrow our search.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000045.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="46" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Here we can see all of the cases found in Kentucky under the Lemon Law keynumber.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000046.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="47" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>What if you don’t have a case covering the legal topic you’re interested in?  Then you would access the key number system by selecting the key number link at the top of the screen.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000047.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="48" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>There are several ways to search using the key number system online.  Let’s start by searching for a key number.  To search for a key number with terms use the search box.  Let’s try the term lemon law.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000048.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="49" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Now we will select Kentucky as our jurisdiction and  we will  put a check in the box of the most appropriate Topic and Key Number for our research.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000049.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="50" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Here we can see all of the cases found in Kentucky under the Lemon Law keynumber.&lt;br&gt;Note: These are the same results that we got searching from the headnotes in the Day case.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000050.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="51" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>You can also search by using the digest outline.  To search using the digest outline select West Key Number Digest Outline&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000051.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="52" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Scroll through the list of topics and key numbers&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000052.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="53" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Until you find the one that best suits your research needs.  We will select keynumber 206, topic motor vehicles: “lemon” laws&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000053.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="54" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>We will designate Kentucky again as our jurisdiction.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Note: we could also add additional terms in the search terms box to further refine our search.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000054.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="55" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Again, we get the same set of results.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000055.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="56" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Finally, you can also search by KeySearch.  KeySearch  will take you through a query formation process that involves pointing and clicking your way through an organized list of legal topics, which come from the West Key Number System.  To search by KeySearch select the KeySearch link.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000056.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="57" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Use a keyword search to locate topics &amp;amp; key numbers.  You may need to be more general with your search terms.  We will start with the term lemon law.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000057.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="58" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Notice, none of these topics seem on point.  Let’s try to go broader.  Since lemon law issues are often found in conjunction with warranty claims, let’s try searching for the term warranty.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000058.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="59" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Here we can see that warranty is a valid category in keysearch and we can continue pointing and clicking  &lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000059.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="60" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Next we will select Kentucky State cases as the database we want to search&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000060.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="61" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Here you can see we have gotten 4 results instead of the 2 we had gotten with our previous searches.  By broadening our search with the term warranty we have increased the number of results we received.  We also still pulled back the same 2 lemon law cases that our previous searches found.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000061.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="62" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Now we will talk about Lexis headnotes.  Lexis headnotes are a little different from Westlaw headnotes.  Lexis headnotes  are still organized by broad topics and then progressively subdivided by narrower subjects, but Lexis headnote subjects tend to be broader concepts than the West key numbers.  Also, Lexis headnotes do not editorialize they  actually lift language straight from the text of the case.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To search by headnotes,  use  the Lexis Search by ‘Topic &amp;amp; Headnote’ tab&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here we will use a search term to retrieve desired cases and select appropriate headnotes.  We will search for the term lemon law.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000062.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="63" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>A list of headnotes will appear and you will select the most appropriate for your research needs.  In this case we will select lemon law.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000063.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="64" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Option 1 will  let you search for lemon laws across  all cases, statutes, and secondary sources. Option 2 is for searching  just cases.  This option searches for the cases assigned to a particular headnote subject. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We will use Option 2 and select Kentucky state cases as our jurisdiction.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000064.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="65" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content>Here we see the results of our search.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000065.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="66" xmlns="">
		<title>Updating Case Law</title>
		<content>Updating Case Law Westlaw Keycite Symbols Lexis Shepard’s Symbols      </content>
		<related-content>As you have been looking at the cases in this presentation you may have noticed several different symbols appearing at the top of the page next to the case name.  These symbols are called citators and they are used to indicate whether the case you are looking at is still good law.  As a general rule, cases with a red flag or red stop sign may no longer be good law and should not be relied upon without doing further research.  Similarly, cases with a yellow flag or yellow triangle should be used with caution because they may have been distinguished by other court rulings.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Citators will be covered more in depth in another lesson, but you should keep in mind that in addition to helping you determine whether a case is still ok to cite, citators can also help you find more cases like the case you are interested in in both your jurisdiction and in other jurisdictions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000066.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="67" xmlns="">
		<title>Additional Resources</title>
		<content>Additional Resources Westlaw Lexis Westlaw eLearningUnder “Getting Started on Westlaw” select the Cases Tab Lexis HeadnotesRetrieving All Headnotes on a Topic </content>
		<related-content>For additional case law resources try the following Westlaw and Lexis tutorials.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This concludes our lesson on case law.  If you have any questions regarding these materials please contact your legal writing professor or a reference librarian for further assistance.  Thank you.&lt;br&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000067.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
